[Music]
hello everyone and welcome to this lunch
event session on flexible update
management um today I'll walk you
through the changes we're making to
update management for your business Cent
for environments from version 25
onwards in short we're massively
increasing the flexibility with which
you can manage your environment updates
in response to uh feedback from some of
our biggest customers and partners um by
doing this we're meeting the require
ments of update diverse customers so
these are customers that are running
24hour shops and don't want plan
downtime every month or customers that
have extensive testing requirements um
that they don't want to repeat for every
new version every
month um we're doing it also to spread
and reduce the workload of Partners so
partners that that manage many customer
environments uh have many updates to run
uh every major update and by increasing
the flexibility with which these can be
scheduled um we can spread and reduce
their
workload and then finally um having
fewer updates or more flexib flexibility
in managing these updates also makes it
uh possible to operate more efficiently
so whenever exceptions are needed um you
can now reschedule from the admin Center
yourself rather than having to go
through customer
support um the major update cycle for
the past couple of release has um looked
like this um so as with every major
release we start with a preview period
um that runs every March and every
September
and then every October and April we ship
a new major
version um for the P releases um this
major update would be scheduled around 7
days after it's first made available on
every environment and then from that
moment on administrators would have 60
days to um schedule that update and run
it after that a grace period would start
um and then finally an enforced update
period would start in which any
incompatible extensions are
uninstalled now what we heard a lot from
our customers is that these 60 days are
not enough in some cases so what we're
changing with version 25 and further is
um that the update period is increasing
from 60 days to 5 months so now when
version 25 ships on the 1st of October
uh any environments that are updating to
this version we'll have until the 1st of
March to do so um after the 1st of March
we will start a grace period similar to
before uh but the grace period is
shortened so for one month the month of
March um we'll run the updates every
week um and it's no longer possible to
schedule it for a later date and then
finally from the 1st of April we'll
start the enforced update period so in
this period um any environments that
still have filed to update because of
incompatibilities in installed
extensions uh will be forced updated by
uninstalling those extensions as part of
the update with these changes the the
grace period now aligns with the preview
period for the next version so the
moment the grace period for version 24
starts will start the preview for
version 26 in March next year and then
in April when we ship version 26 we'll
start the force updating from version 24
to version
25 um with these changes um we'll refer
to an update cycle only for major
updates so the update cycle as I just
said starts with a preview period that
lasts for 30
days um after the preview period will
start the regular update period this
will always last for five calendar
months and the end date is fixed so for
the update that ships in October the end
date of the update period will always be
the 1st of March and for the update that
ships in April the end date will always
be the 1st of
September um after the update period we
continue with the grace period which um
is shortened but behaves exactly as
Grace periods uh for previous releases
so during the grace periods we're
scheduling the update every week it will
run on the scheduled date and if it
fills or reschedule it for a week later
um during this period is not possible to
postpone the update uh to a later date
so if we schedule uh the update after a
field attempt to run 7 days after that
attempt you can reschedule it to an
earlier day you can say I want to try it
again after 5 days but it's not possible
to reschedule to a later date uh let's
say to reschedule after 10
days um this gr period last for a month
so uh in short that means that every
environment update will be attempted
four times and after that we'll start
the enforced update period so this Peri
period behaves much like the grace
period with the exception that as part
of this update will uninstall any apps
that are not compatible with the next
version of business Central and also in
this time it's not possible to postpone
the update any
further um minor updates on the other
end don't have an update cycle anymore
so we'll continue to ship them every
month um and the default scheduling is
unchanged so every month we'll ship it
um 7 days after we ship it it will be
scheduled on your environment um and
then you can res schedule it um but what
is changing is that you can now opt out
of automatic scheduling so we introduce
a new environment level setting uh on
your environment that you can use to say
I want uh this update to be scheduled
automatically yes or no and if you up
out we will ship minor updates they'll
be available on your environment to
update to but we will not schedule for
you and you'd have to take action in the
admin Center to get a minor
update um what's also changing is with
minor updates being opt
um you can uh fall behind multiple
versions so if you don't install the
latest minor every month you could be
behind a few miners at some point um
what we're changing now is that if you
schedule an update you can select the
target version for that update so you go
into the admin Senter you want a
schedule an update and you can take any
version later than the version your
environment is on which makes it
possible to um skip some
versions and then finally uh what's also
new is that you can create create
environments on any supported version so
in the admin Center when you create a
new environment you'll be able to select
any version number that we support um
instead of the current behavior of just
supporting the latest version um of
course if you create the environments by
logging in to an tenant that doesn't
have any business censal environment yet
we'll always create the latest uh we'll
always create an environment on the
latest version these changes are rolling
out gradually over the course of um the
major releasee so the public review is
starting in October 2024 when we ship
version 25 and it only applies to
Microsoft localized
environments um that means that
Microsoft localized environments they
get a new update cycle so they get the
five month window um and the update 25.0
when we ship it will be schedulable
until the 1st of March
2025 um minor updates will ship as I
said before on these environments as
well and after you've updated to version
25.0 um you'll have until the first of
September so the end of the update
period for version 25 uh to schedule any
minor updates that you want to install
in your
environment uh what is not possible
during the public preview is to change
the target version so after you update
to 25.0 let's say you want to get to
25.3 but you don't necessarily want to
update to 25.1 or 25.2 you still have to
go through those versions um to get to
25.3 so you won't be able to go straight
from 25.0 to 25.3 as an example
um then General availability is going to
follow towards the end of this release
wave um at that point these changes will
be available globally so also the more
flexible update management will be
available to partner localized
environments um and at that point also
the admin Center changes will come so
we'll introduce the opt out for
automatic scheduling um so environments
can choose not to receive miners
automatically anymore um at that point
it will be possible to change the update
Target version as well so it'll be
possible to skip versions
um we'll introduce the API changes for
update scheduling so um just for
partners and customers that that
automate the scheduling of environments
the API endpoints in the admin Center
API that we've had for this uh will
slightly change to reflect the new
flexibility um those changes are coming
in March um and also from that date on
it'll be possible to create versions or
create environments on any supported
version um and then finally there's
going to be some communication changes
so you can expect the email
notifications to slightly change
reflecting the more flexible update
management um and for partners in
particular that automate or alert based
on the Telemetry signals um these
signals will also Chang with the
properties uh applicable to the update
so the signals that we've had for a few
years at this point are going to change
and if you're uh if youve built on top
of that there's going to be U some
break-in changes that are going to come
in March with all this increased
flexibility we don't think that the best
practices uh around update management
are going to change so for most most
environments um the best course of
action will be to install the minor
updates when we ship it every month and
not fall
behind um and so our best practices
remain unchanged as well um we recommend
everyone to keep environments updatable
um stay current with the extensions make
sure that extensions installed on the
environment can always update to any
later version of business Central um and
that is important to stay informed on
product changes so we might introduce
features that a customer really
needs um in minor updates and it would
be best if that environment is updatable
to that version to make sure that the
customer receives the features that they
really need at the time that we ship
them um this flexibility IT addresses
some specific concerns from specific
customers and partners and for those we
really encourage them to use it and to
use the
flexibility um but for most customers
the best course of action would be to uh
remain to the default scheduling every
month and that includes flexible update
Management in 2024 release Wave 2 thank
you